Rajath Jaiprakash

🗘 rajathjn | 🛅 rajath-jaiprakash | 🏶 Portfolio | 💌 rajathjnx@gmail.com | 🖡 +91-9900852849

Summary

Site Reliability Engineer II with around 3 years of specialized experience in Infrastructure Automation, CI/CD, and Logging/Monitoring pipelines. Achieved 50% reduction in manual operations by designing and implementing 20+Ansible roles across production environments. Demonstrated expertise in troubleshooting complex infrastructure issues by reducing system downtime by 30% through enhanced observability solutions.

Skills

| Programming | Python, Shell Scripting, C++, Powershell Scripting |
|----------------------|--|
| Certifications | The Linux Foundation: LFS162, Red Hat Certified Engineer (EX294) |
| Tools & Technologies | Ansible, Docker, Kubernetes, GitHub Actions, Jenkins, Elastic Stack (ELK), OTel, Syslog- |
| | ng, TIG Stack, Prometheus, NagiosXI |

Work Experience

Akamai Technologies, Inc. | Site Reliability Engineer II

Oct 2024 - Present

- Architected end-to-end **CI/CD pipelines** for our Access Border Routers by integrating it with our AAA Simulators and custom deployment scripts, reducing deployment time by **75%** and our downtime to just **30 seconds**.
- Engineered fault-tolerant system by developing **Python** based auto-remediation scripts for **8 critical services**, significantly reduced manual recovery procedures and improved service availability.
- Identified, Troubleshot and Solved a Business critical compliance issue which impacted our 6WIND VSRs, across 18
 Distributed Edge sites.

Akamai Technologies, Inc. | Site Reliability Engineer

July 2022 - Oct 2024

- Improved our deployment workflow by crafting **20+ Ansible** roles for automated configuration management, reducing deployment errors and cutting rollout time from days to hours across **4 environments**.
- Executed the complex migration of **18 production logging servers** by designing comprehensive transition plan and implementing parallel cutover strategy, maintaining near **100%** service availability and processing over **250K+ daily transactions** without interruption.
- Enhanced logging infrastructure by optimizing, migrating and upgrading our **ELK Cluster** to efficiently handle **150GB+** of daily logs, resulting in a **300%** increase in log search performance and enabling real-time anomaly detection for **20+** critical services.
- Spearheaded DevOps knowledge sharing initiative by conducting 6 technical workshops for 30+ engineers over 3 different time-zones, resulting in 40% fewer deployment-related incidents across development teams.
- Enhanced monitoring for 200+ nodes by implementing hierarchical alerting structure in NagiosXI using InfluxDB and OpenSNMP Collector, reducing false positives and redundant alerts by 70%.

Projects

ClipForge - AI Driven Video Processing Pipeline

- Engineered an end-to-end local and open-source automated video generation pipeline by integrating WhisperX, FFm-peg, and AI agents created using Langchain Python. Project has received over 77k+ impressions to date.
- Built AI-based metadata generation, improving **SEO** and content discoverability by **40%**. Implemented automated **CI/CD** testing via **GitHub Actions**.
- Created a **Dockerized** deployment workflow and real-time **Discord** notification system, supporting 100+ daily video operations.

Education

PES University, Bangalore

2018 - 2022

B.Tech, Electronics and Communication Engineering (Minors in Computer Science and Engineering), GPA: 8.99

Publications & Leadership

IEEE CONECCT 2022: Analog Front End Modelling of Miniature CMOS Image Sensor

• Led a cross-functional research team by coordinating circuit design and simulation efforts, resulting in the publication of an innovative medical imaging technology with potential applications in minimally invasive procedures with a power consumption of just 4.8 mW.